Finding Aid for Sidney Fine Papers, 1949-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sidney Fine Papers 1949-2000, 1960-2000
Fine, Sidney, 1920-
8 linear feet
0527 Aa 2
Professor of history at the University of Michigan. Correspondence and topical files relating to his teaching and other activities at the University of Michigan, to his scholarly interests, and to his participation in scholarly organizations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Sidney Fine (donor no. 3500 ) and came to the library in 2000. Additional papers were received in 2002.
The collection is open to research.
Dr. Sidney Fine was born in 1920 in Cleveland, Ohio. He received his B.A. from Western Reserve University in 1942, served in the Navy from 1942-1946, and earned both a M.A. (1944) and Ph.D. (1948) in history from the University of Michigan. Dr. Fine is a specialist in modern American history, with interest in the history of the labor movement, the New Deal, and the history of Michigan and its political environment. He has written and edited over fifteen books and articles.
Sidney Fine's first appointment at the University of Michigan was as a teaching assistant in 1946. He accepted a position as a UM instructor in 1948 and was subsequently appointed as an assistant professor, an associate professor, then a full professor in 1949 in the History Department. Dr. Fine acted as advisor to masters and doctoral students, served on many doctoral committees, and he was chairman of the department in the early 1940s. He was named the Richard Hudson Research Professor of History, the Andrew Dickson White Distinguished Professor of History, the Henry Russel Lecturer, and was named the "Professor of the Year" for the state of Michigan in 1986.
Dr. Fine was very active in the University of Michigan community, serving on numerous committees in the College of Literature, Science & the Arts (LSA) and the general university community. He was the advisor for student associations such as Phi Beta Kappa and Phi Kappa Phi, and he served on the executive and advisory committees of UM libraries, including the Bentley Historical Library, the Gerald R. Ford Library, and the Friends of University Library. Dr. Fine was very involved in library and archive issues nationally, serving on the Archives Advisory Council and the Public Documents Commission. He also consulted on several UM-related and private projects such as the Ford Corporate History Project, the UAW Oral History Project, and television series on labor history. Dr. Fine was a member of many professional societies and served on the editorial board of several history journals.
Sidney Fine in now retired from the University of Michigan, although he continues to be involved in many UM activities, library groups, and historical societies across the country. He married Jean Schechter in 1942 and has two daughters.
The papers of Sidney Fine consist of correspondence, memos, and reports related to his professional activities at the University of Michigan and his association with many academic journals, professional societies, public committees, and other history-related projects. The collection has been divided in five series: Personal, University of Michigan, Other Professional Activities, Correspondence, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Fine, Sidney, 1920-; Historians--United States.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fine, Sidney, 1920-; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Personal
  The Personal series (to approximately 1989; 1 folder) includes a copy of Fine's resume and various papers relating to his professional career and appointment at the University of Michigan.
  - Biographical clippings (Box 1)
  - Personal papers, to 1989 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series (1949-1999, 2 linear feet) consists of memos, meeting minutes, committee reports, and correspondence related to Fine's career at the University of Michigan. The series is divided into three subseries: History Department, Committees, and Libraries. The History Department subseries includes materials related specifically to Fine's appointments in the History Department as both a faculty member and as a department chair in the early 1940s. The Committees subseries contains memos and reports related to several university committees on which Sidney Fine served, including the Faculty Reform Committee, the Committee on College Priorities, LSA and Rackham dean search committees, the Research Club, and the Russel Lectureship Committee. The Libraries subseries consists of memos, correspondence, and reports related to Fine's participation on the executive committees and planning groups for the Bentley Historical Library/Michigan Historical Collections, Gerald R. Ford Library, the Friends of University Library, and other library-related committees on the UM campus.
  - History Department
    - Memos, Reports, Correspondence 1949-1999, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Course-related Materials (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Commission on Graduation Requirements 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Committee on College Priorities 1973-1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Distinguished Faculty Achievement Awards Committee 1969-1985 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Reform Coalition 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Future of the University Press 1986 (Box 1)
    - LSA Dean's Search Committee 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1963-1983 (Box 1)
    - NEH Journalism Fellows 1975-1979 (Box 1)
    - Phi Beta Kappa 1972-1976 (Box 1)
    - Phi Kappa Phi 1959-1966 (Box 1)
    - Rackham Deanship Search Committee 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Research Club 1962-1984, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Russel Lectureship Committee 1977-1999 (Box 1)
    - Scientific Club 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - William W. Cook Lectureship Committee 1973-1989 (Box 1)
  - Libraries
    - Bentley Historical Library/Michigan Historical Collections (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee 1960-1999, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Director Search 1980-1981, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Friends of University Library
      - Board of Directors 1987-1999, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Gerald R. Ford Library
      - Advisory Council 1979-1988 (Box 2)
      - Building dedication 1981 (Box 2)
      - Director Search 1979-1981 (Box 2)
      - Foundation Grant Review Committee 1989 (Box 2)
    - LSA Library Committee 1960-1968 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1971-1990 (Box 2)
    - Walter P. Reuther Library of Labor and Urban Affairs
      - Executive Committee 1983-1992 (Box 2)
- Other Professional Activities
  The Other Professional Activities series (1958-1999, 2 linear feet) consists of correspondence, reports, memos, and project proposals relating to Sidney Fine's non-UM professional activities. The series is divided into three subseries: Committees, Journals/Societies, and Projects. The Committees subseries contains letters, reports, and notes related to several public committees of which Fine was a member, including the Archives Advisory Council and the Public Documents Commission. The Journals/Societies subseries includes a large volume of correspondence and reports related to Sidney Fine's participation on the editorial boards of history journals such as Labor History and Michigan Historical Review and his active membership in professional societies including the Organization of American Historians, the Mississippi Valley Historical Society, and the American Historical Association. The Projects subseries includes correspondence, reports, and meeting minutes concerning several of Sidney Fine's history-related projects and consulting jobs such as the Ford Corporate History Project, UAW Oral History Project, and television programs about labor history.
  - Committees
    - Archives Advisory Council 1968-1972, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation 1977-1980 (Box 3)
    - Committee on the Historian and the Federal Government 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Emergency Committee to Preserve the National Archives 1980 (Box 3)
    - Public Documents Commission 1976-1977, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Journals/Societies
    - AHA Committee to Collect the Basic Quantitative Data of American Political History 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - American Historical Association 1961-1970 (Box 3)
    - Holocaust Memorial Center 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - Jewish Welfare Federation of Detroit 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Labor History 1963-1984, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Michigan Historical Review 1986-1998 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Quarterly 1975-1999, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Mississippi Valley Historical Society/Journal of American History 1964-1968 (Box 4)
    - National Museum of American History 1986 (Box 4)
    - Organization of American Historians 1967-1981 (Box 4)
    - Philip Taft Labor History Award 1977-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Reviews in American History 1972-1982 (Box 4)
    - Wittenberg Review 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Projects
    - Crowell Collier Publishing Company/Special Editor in U.S. History 1962-1967 (Box 4)
    - Ford Corporate History Project 1986-1994, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Maurice Sugar-Research Correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1976-1987 (Box 4)
    - New American Nation Series 1959 (Box 4)
    - Salzburg Seminar in American Studies 1958-1961 (Box 4)
    - "Twentieth Century Trade Union Woman" Oral History Project 1975-1981 (Box 4)
    - UAW Oral History Project 1958-1974, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - WGBH American Labor History Series 1975-1984, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Wittenberg University-Curriculum Consultant 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - WNET Liberty Series 1974-1977, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series spans the years 1964-2000, but in fact there are few letters prior to 1970 and from 1979 to 1990. The letters are from colleagues, students, and friends and are largely personal in character.
  - 1964 1970-1977 (Box 5)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - 1988-1989 (scattered) (Box 6)
    (almost no correspondence was received from the 1980s)
  - 1990-1992 (Box 6)
  - 1993-1996 (Box 7)
  - 1997-2000 (Box 8)
- Visual Materials
  Visual Materials includes two videotapes, one a visual biography of Professor Fine, the other a taping of a lecture given by Fine as recipient of the Golden Apple Award.
  - Videotape: U-M Hillel Golden Apple Award: Sidney Fine's "Last Lecture" March 29, 1993, vhs (Box 8)
  - Videotape: "Movietone News Salutes Sidney Fine" circa 1990, U-matic copy; ca. 15 min. (Box 8)
    (humorous and lighthearted look at the career of Professor Fine)